okay do a short
meditation and then get to the
class let's start with your
breath single object just your breath
there's nothing else in the world just
your
breath
e e
and come to a golden Moon so on the side
of the mountain sunlight pouring
in covering the room with a deep gold
color all the objects in the room are
covered in a deep golden color sunlight
if your in mind leaves the golden color
bring it back
relax into the golden
color feel a sense of contentment to
stay just there without planning
anything
or being aware of this
room just be satisfied to be on the
golden color coming through the
window
e e
look at the sky look out the window see
the sky deep blue sky and the
sky don't think of anything
else be content to stay in the sky
relax into the
sky e
and drop your view down from the sky to
the
mountains these mountains are
distant and they are
separating from the window from your
house by large Valley covered in also
covered in the late afternoon
life try
to focus on the feeling of
expansiveness it will help you meditate
in about 3 or 4
minutes e
check your face for any ttention the
especially the corners of your
mouth and
the forehead between the
eyebrows try to pay attention to the top
of your
eyelids is there any tension
there and release them e
bring the mind in back in the Golden
Moon be aware of yourself
sitting in the Deep Golden
Light and then request your your heart
teacher whoever that may be to come and
sit in front of you very close like
knees touching
knees try to feel their presence not as
a visualization but as a real
person uh their chest is moving up and
down with the
breath you can feel the
warmth of their body on the front of
your body
you can smell that
subtle fragrance that comes from the
skin when they look at you they're
linking
sometimes relax into the
teaching try to bring up a sense of
contentment to stay in this room
quietly just you two
silent warm in the Golden Light just try
very hard to just be
contented to stay
there looking at their
face looking into their eyes and just
stay
there you don't have anything else to do
you don't need to worry about anything
else right now just
look into their eyes feel the mutual
love and surrender quietly into
it
e e
check and see if any of the classical
problems of meditation are coming up
let's the Mind
feel dull or
unclear maybe a little sleepy or
tired you're losing the freshness of
your
attention or watch for the opposite
problem uh your mind
is little bit Yancy it wants to think
about lunch or your plans for this
evening
and uh you
can circum navigate those classical
problems of meditation simply by
bringing up the sensation of n n is
that
contentment to stay with the object and
enjoyment of the object which is your
teacher's eyes so try to
bring up an emotion of
contentment with staying on your
teacher's
eyes then you won't have the two famous
problems of either
feeling that the mind is not fresh or
thinking about your plans for this
evening or
tomorrow a sense of contentment to stay
on your teacher's
life
e
e e
and slowly come back to this
room and you can open your eyes
to so
uh where did Nick go
we were examining
me
uh we're on the subject of
emptiness which by the end of the week
we're going to have a great what do you
call it there going to be a great
Confluence of the two subjects
meditation and emptiness like by the end
of the week there will be a great
joining of these two
subjects uh probably tomorrow sometime
something uh
but but we were saying you know the
Buddhist have this idea of emptiness or
or no self and then we were exploring
what that means and we were trying very
hard to make it practical like is it
something you could actually use in your
life to make your life more successful
and happy so we were examining Nick for
a bunch of days now and we were trying
to locate the Nick which does exist we
call yuu do and then the Nick which
doesn't exist which is called me du so
so there when you whenever you're
looking at nit or anybody else by the
way you're supposed to turn this on
yourself right so Chelsea turns it on
Chelsea retes turns it on retes uh
anytime you look at Nick or especially
when Nick looks at
nick uh there are two Nicks appearing to
the mind to his mind and they are mixed
like water and milk one of the Nicks
exists and anything he does with regard
to that Nick is successful and
meaningful and then there's another Nick
mixed in there which doesn't exist and
then anytime he's relating to that Nick
he's open
to uh emotional you know getting upset
or getting angry or getting jealous
all negative emotions of the Mind depend
upon the neck that doesn't exist to come
up if you didn't have mixed in with your
perceptions of
Nick uh and a Nick who didn't exist then
you wouldn't have negative
emotions negative emotions depend for
their very
existence Upon A Vidya or ignorance
about who Nick is and and they they they
rely
upon uh the perception of a Nick that
doesn't exist at all okay so if we could
identify that Nick which we call gaka
right if we could identify that Nick
gaka means the thing that was never
there if we could identify the part of
Nick that appears to us but which
doesn't really
exist then we then you would never have
a negative emotion again and that's the
Buddhist definition of nirvana okay
Nirvana is not where you disappear and
you go off somewhere or something like
that uh you simply
come to a very sensitive awareness of
the Nick that was never there and if you
get if you reach that awareness you
can't have a negative emotion anymore
and that's Nirvana that's the meaning of
nirvana much later you get to uh
Enlightenment but Nirvana comes before
and you don't you don't go anywhere and
you don't look any different to other
people and it's not like you just blink
out of existence or something like that
uh it's that you can never be angry or
jealous or upset again it's not possible
because all of those are dependent upon
the Nick that doesn't exist so once you
get good at identifying that Nick that
doesn't exist the the measure of
your understanding of emptiness is that
your negative emotions will start to
lessen okay so if you want to know if
you're on the right
track as far as emptiness there should
be a correspond responding lessening of
your negative
emotions if your negative emotions are
getting more then your emptiness view is
getting
less okay uh let's give a real example
some books go missing to use a
vancouverism uh some books go missing in
the bookstore and then Nick was let's
say Nick was supposed to manage the
bookstore and then
somebody comes in you know Rebecca and
her other uh lesser
Chieftains they they come in uh to the
bookstore and they're discussing you
know uh they don't notice that Nick is
there and then they're discussing do you
know we have some books missing and then
somebody says do you think we can really
trust Nick you
know uh and then uh Nick hears it
and then immediately arises
a in the heart is a tiny fire or a tiny
burning in the
heart which relates to your heart chakra
actually and the movement of Prana in
your heart chakra but anyway in real
terms it feels like a your heart jerks
or your heart twists a little bit and
then you start to feel upset and you
start to
think I I don't deserve to be first of
all I didn't steal the bats
and then but the main thing is I don't
deserve to be blamed for them you know I
I don't deserve to be blamed for them
then we were saying that in
this system of
thinking uh which you can call Buddhism
but I don't think it matters we were in
communist China we Ted to thousands of
people we didn't mention the word
Buddhism we wore business suits we
looked like Mormon
missionaries uh and then uh you know we
were
just regular people who had a new way of
thinking and I don't think it matters
what you call it to me it doesn't matter
if you keep a picture of budha or
Muhammad or Jesus or I don't care I
don't care what's on your I don't
absolutely I absolutely don't care what
pictures hanging on your wall I
personally don't keep a lot of pictures
them people give me dozens of them I
give them
away uh I have one picture that I like
to hang I like to hang do but I some
artist in Mongolia painted it for me so
it means a lot to me and sometimes I let
soapa be there because I like him uh but
that's all I don't really care it
doesn't matter to me uh so this is not a
Buddhist thing it's just a it's just a
thing everybody can use and then you
keep your own pictures and that's okay
we went to Ireland we went to a
cathedral in gway and this guy had a big
conversion and he said oh I'm going to
become a Buddhist I said between you and
me you know when your daughter gets
married are you going to have like a six
star blue guy there uh or are you going
to take her to a nice Irish Cathedral
and have some organ music and he's like
yeah I guess you you know
uh so
anyway can you use this according to
this system of thinking all objects in
the world are coming from seeds within
our own
minds everything we see every body we
see and everything anyone ever says to
us is Flowing from seeds in our own mind
which were planted there when we did the
same thing to somebody else okay that's
all there's no inexplicable object in
the world there's no object in the world
that doesn't have a cause and there's no
object in the world which doesn't have a
cause in how we're treating other people
okay absolutely there's even the ging
Dar used to say the slightest Breeze
coming into the window and you feel a
little brush on your cheek that also has
a
cost from something you did to somebody
okay everything around you every detail
of the carpet every grain of the wood
every not the placement of every not on
the wood they each have a cause in
something we did to somebody else okay
and then we see those things okay
so it's absolutely positively untrue
that Nick could be never be blamed un
unjustly okay it's true that he didn't
steal the
book but but in the moment of being
censured by somebody else in the moment
of being criticized by somebody
else if he follows this
system his natural reaction to being
criticized should should be only to
think why why is my mind projecting a
person criticizing what what am what
criticism have I given to other in the
last few weeks that's all okay by the
way you should feel
better that Co seeds are always smaller
than their result seeds are way way
smaller than their results if you get to
the point where you're standing in the
bookstore um offering to manage it as a
volunteer and the Big Chief of the
retreat is blaming it for something you
can take comfort in the fact that the
criticism you gave to someone else must
have been much less because it increased
is hundredfold
in as it ripens in the ground of the
mind okay so you don't have to go
looking for the last time you shot
somebody or something like that you
could think I must be in a small way in
my own small way I must be critical of
someone else even mentally right then
you just go after that criticism and you
wipe it out you stop it and then uh
Rebecca comes in and says you know I'm
sorry we we found out that you know the
money was dropped and uh
it wasn't your fault at all and actually
you're doing a great job in the
bookstore and we hope you'll do it for
the next three
years you know like that
okay but what we've been
exploring is that
uh is that Nick that comes up when he's
first
blamed that Nick who didn't deserve to
be blamed because in this system there's
no such thing you deserve everything
that happens to you even if it's unjust
you know even if you didn't steal
anything you deserve to be accused
because you accus somebody else of
something similar okay and but it's not
a kind of a
fatalistic understanding of being blamed
it's not like you sit there and let
people blame you forever you know it's
not that's not the point of it the point
is that you go after your own tendency
of criticizing others and that makes you
a better person it's not that you sit
there and say okay it's okay for Rebecca
to blame me and it's also not necessary
to stay quiet you can speak up and say
you know I I didn't steal anything you
know it may or may not work according to
your seats okay be aware but it's okay
to say something ultimately the only way
to fix the situation is to go after your
own
criticism going after the seats doesn't
disallow taking normal actions okay just
be aware that they may not work going
after the the seeds always works going
after the seeds always works but in the
meantime you can also tell Rebecca I
didn't steal him whether she'll believe
you or not is is uncertain because that
method is is
uncertain I my personally I like to say
you know Becky I didn't steal anything
and I'm going to work on my seeds of
criticism you know and then she may say
you're stupid or smart uh but be aware
that clarifying things to her is not a
cause for her to stop criticizing you
okay as you know from all the years of
negotiating with your partner or anybody
else it may work it may not work it's
not the cause but that doesn't mean you
shouldn't try it's okay to try just be
aware it may not work ultimately you
have to go over after the seeds you have
to examine yourself if you've been
critical of someone else that's all and
then Becky will discover the money it's
very profound in way okay
so we're back to the text
now so we were talking about a
magician who had cast a spell on an
audience uh with Mantra which is the
original meaning of
Mantra the original function of mantras
was for casting spells and then he
throws some substance powders on the
people maybe they were psych tropics I
don't know uh but then people would see
a a cow or they would see a
horse and the magician also sees a carow
horse but their relationship the cow or
the horse is different because they
don't believe in it okay they see it but
they know it's
a A fantasm or or a magical tra
okay this is interesting
okay
uh even though it's a losery the horse
can walk around
okay even though it's a losery the horse
can walk around the circle we were
giving example of a longhorn steer and a
crowd was a little nervous cuz it was it
was what do you call it snorting and
going like this you know so even though
it it's imaginary it can do things it
can walk it can threaten the crowd you
know it can do
that there there's a very important word
for those of you studying toon it's
uh is related
to this spelling is different okay those
of you who
care and then the spelling of the other
one they both mean crazy okay they're
both Tibetan words for crazy sometimes
they drop off the n and they say Noah
for
example crazy maker is a scriptural word
for drugs and alcohol okay
so that which makes you stupid and crazy
is the is the scriptural word for
alcohol and drug okay so
here is a very important word for those
of you who care about learning about
tietan means literally it means uncrazy
not crazy okay it means
means despite the fact that everything
is coming from our own minds from seeds
planted there by how we treat others it
still functions
nun you know it's not like cuckoo or
anything it still functions perfectly
rationally so means like perfectly
rationally the fact that seeds grow
plants and the fact that gasoline makes
a car run and you know these these are
all perfectly rational okay there's
nothing weird about them you have to
reconcile the fact that everything is
Flowing from your mind and the fact that
everything works in perfectly rationally
gasoline does make cars go aspirin can
stop a headache yoga can make you thin
and strong you know those are
all is perfectly rational okay literally
it means
not we see
that
sorry yeah that's
[Music]
okay very
famous it means
the things around you in the world are
only projections from your mind in in
majima they use the word nominal they
are flowing from names don't think of it
as names that's a little tricky okay
don't think of that when they say name
only or everything exists only
n name right
n don't get hung up on the nominal thing
you know I I think it's the wrong way to
go what name means in the study of
emptiness is the little images that your
mind makes and puts on things
okay Nick you know you go like this with
your finger
Nick Nick when you go like Nick that's a
picture in your head you're referring to
a picture in your head you can call it a
name that's the real name that's what
names really are names are not
verbalizations the Dharma goes into that
Mings are not sorry names are not
syllables and tones and sounds the real
names are the images in your own mind
and the real names are are they flower
from the seeds planted in your mind when
you were either good or bad to others
okay so your actions towards others
plant seeds in your mind which flower
into what are called words or names and
those names you apply to different
objects Nick or camera or carpet so stop
thinking dharm says stop thinking of
name as a sound start thinking of the
word name as that little picture which
is born from the seeds in your mind
which were planted by how well you took
care of others that's names so when we
say everything exists in name only what
we really mean is all the people around
you are just images coming up from in
your mind depending on the seeds you
planted before okay very
important shindu and and therefore they
are not real okay in what sense are they
not
real
uh they're not what you thought the
appearance and the reality are different
okay it it looked like those things
existed out there in theend
of your mind but the reality is that
everyone around you and everything
around you is Flowing from your own mind
okay let see then people don't freak out
okay don't go to some extreme don't say
I'm living in my head that's also not
true okay is everything coming from your
mind yes are you living inside your head
and there's nobody else in the universe
no why cuz your mind is projecting other
people outside of you and that makes
them real people outside of you okay are
they projections of your mind yes are
they are you stuck in your head no why
the seeds are projecting them as outside
people and that makes them outside
people so you can relate to them that's
fine okay don't freak out don't think
there's nobody to like have a friendship
with or that you're stuck in the whole
universe by yourself it's not true
people around you are coming from you
but they're real people outside of you
got it okay M La
sorry something didn't so the Nick who
is coming from Nick's mind he can do all
the normal stuff he does collect Karma
he does he's either nice or bad to other
people he does experience the
consequences of his actions okay he he
projects a doer and he projects an
experiencer of the consequences of his
actions okay he Pro he projects a Nick
who's an actor and he projects the Nick
who experiences the consequences of his
actions so we can say that the whole
working of things is nun May it's
perfectly rational everything is okay
people do stuff and people get the
results of what they do that's all that
whole system is fine is it coming from
your mind yes is it still real excuse me
that's what makes it real don't ask me
is it still real much less it's not only
real it couldn't have been real if it
existed out there without your
mind all right you got to get used to
that the way you thought it always was
that's
unreal okay a car that could run on gas
without your giving other people rights
is unreal there's no no such thing
there's no such thing you could put gas
in a car I borrowed Darcy's truck
yesterday it was full she I don't know I
think she drove somewhere and got the
full of gas and I got into it I was in
Prescot and I'm like click click click
even the battery seemed to be working
cuz it did click but nothing
happened okay you can have gas it
doesn't make a cargo
does that mean gas doesn't make a car go
no gas which is imbued with my goodness
by giving other people rides on a
regular basis will make my car
go if it's not imbued with the same
goodness it won't make my car go I can
even have an extra take of that kind of
gas and it still won't start all right
you understand things imbued with your
goodness G things not imbued with your
goodness don't wor they are the same
things the gas is the
same all
[Music]
right now he's going into a beautiful
beautiful place okay it's a it's a
completely new
idea it's a new kind of
thought it's difficult if you haven't
had a good explanation of
emptiness and it's easy if you have had
a good explanation of emptiness okay
it's a no-brainer if someone's been
guiding you the right way on the study
of emptiness otherwise it's very it's
it's a challenge okay but for you guys
it's going to be a no-brain okay here's
the here's the
issue what's the
relationship between
emptiness and and causation
what's the relationship between
emptiness and the way the seeds work in
your
mind okay what's the relationship
between
emptiness and what they call dependent
origination okay I have a beef with that
now I have a beef with that whole thing
first of all it's too long the word is
too long dependent origination it's
eight
syllables Buddha just said
stuff happens from other stuff that's
all he said he didn't say eight sybles
stuff happens
anyway he just said stuff happens from
other
stuff very famous there's a there's a
Sutra called the Sutra on dependent
origination it just consists of one
sentence Lord Buddha said hey stuff
happens because other
stuff so can we reconcile the fact that
things are empty
with the fact that stuff happens from
other
stuff do we have a problem here
and then teachers are constantly going
the wrong way with stuff happens from
other stuff you know people say what
does depend origination mean master